<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>JinnTap Documentation</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Information about publication or distribution</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>JinnTap</head>
            <p>Edit <ref target="https://tei-c.org/">TEI XML</ref> documents using a rich text
               editor. JinnTap preserves the structure of the XML in the editor. There's no need for
               complex transformation steps from TEI to HTML and back. The representation of the
               document in the editor corresponds directly to the XML. TEI elements are converted to
               HTML custom elements, preserving all attributes and structural features.</p>
            <p>While it is very difficult to create a completely generic editor covering the entire
               complexity of TEI, JinnTap tries to be as customizable as possible. To work properly
               in a <choice><abbr>WYSIWYM</abbr><expan>What you see is what you mean</expan></choice> 
               context, the editor needs to be strict with respect to the underlying
               schema. Many elements in TEI are ambiguous with respect to their block or inline
               nature, i.e. they can appear either way. However, the editor has a clear distinction
               between block and inline content<anchor xml:id="fn-m9ic2gkq-e2pwse" type="note" />.
               Therefore JinnTap uses its own schema to define what is allowed in which position. It
               extends the schema used by the underlying editor (<ref
                  target="https://prosemirror.net/">ProseMirror</ref>) to configure additional
               features like toolbar buttons, keyboard shortcuts etc. and is written in JSON.</p>
            <p>Out of the box, the default schema supports:</p>
            <list rend="unordered">
               <item>
                  <p>block level elements like headings, paragraphs, lists</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>elements for inline formatting like <hi rend="code">hi</hi>, <hi rend="code">
                     title</hi></p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>semantic markup for people, organizations, places, terms</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>analytic elements like <hi rend="code">date</hi></p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>footnotes</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div>
               <head>How to edit</head>
               <p>The default starting point for editing is always a paragraph. Use the toolbar
                  buttons to transform it into a heading or another type of block. Note that –
                  according to the gods of TEI – not all elements are allowed at any position. A <hi
                     rend="code">head</hi> may only appear at the start of a division, not after a
                  paragraph. This is where TEI differs from HTML.</p>
               <list rend="unordered">
                  <item>
                     <p>a block will be deleted if you press backspace or delete inside an otherwise
                        empty block.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>within a list-like structure:</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <p>pressing <hi rend="b">tab</hi> will create a nested list below the
                              current one</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p><hi rend="b">shift-tab</hi> moves the list item one level up. If it is
                              already at the top level, it will be transformed into a normal
                              paragraph</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>TEI lists may start with a heading. You can transform the first list
                              item into a <hi rend="code">head</hi> by placing the cursor inside the
                              item and choosing <hi rend="i">Head</hi> from the toolbar.</p>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>to enter an en dash (–), use two hyphens, to create an mdash (—), type
                        three hyphens</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Apply inline markup by selecting some text and pressing a corresponding button.
                  Note that those buttons are toggles, i.e. pressing again will <hi rend="b">remove</hi>
                  the inline markup.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Changing attributes</head>
                  <p>Whenever you move around the document, you'll see how the right-hand panel of
                     the editor changes, showing a form with different fields. Those are the
                     attributes which can be applied to the current element. You can change them any
                     time and the attributes of the element will change accordingly.</p>
                  <p>For example, if you marked something as <hi rend="b">bold</hi> text, you can
                     change it later to <hi rend="u">underline</hi> by placing the cursor inside the
                     element and choosing <hi rend="i">underline</hi> from the dropdown. Don't
                     forget to click the apply button though.</p>
                  <p>To change the attributes of a node which is an ancestor of the node the cursor
                     is currently in, use the breadcrumbs navigation bar on the upper right of the
                     editor. This shows all the ancestor nodes down to the currently active node.
                     Clicking on any of the breadcrumb links will select the corresponding node and
                     the attribute panel will show the attributes assigned to this node.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Divisions</head>
               <p>Use the <hi rend="i">Division </hi>toolbar button to create a <hi rend="code">div</hi>.
                  The new division will always be a child of the division you are currently in. To
                  move the division one level up, position the cursor anywhere inside it, then use
                  the breadcrumb navigation bar to select the division. Next, click on the <hi
                     rend="i">move block up</hi> button in the toolbar.</p>
               <p>You may also move other block-level nodes one level up by following the same
                  procedure. However, please note that moving up a block, which has a following
                  block within the same parent, will split the division.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Semantic annotations</head>
               <p>JinnTap has extended support for <hi rend="i">semantic annotation</hi>, drawing on
                  external registers to identify entities like people, places, organizations or
                  terms. To mark up a person appearing in the text, say: <persName
                     key="gnd-118578537">Karl Marx</persName>, select the name and press the <hi
                     rend="i">Person</hi> toolbar button. The attributes panel to the right will
                  show you a search panel, which is connected to the registered registry. Find the
                  correct person in the list and click on the <hi rend="i">link</hi> button to the
                  left of the entry. This copies the ID of the person from the registry into the <hi
                     rend="code">key</hi> form field.</p>
               <p>Note that selecting an entry from the registry will automatically apply the
                  attribute, so if this is your only change, you don't have to press the <hi
                     rend="i">apply-all</hi> button manually. After selecting, you should also see
                  some additional information about the entity displayed at the very top of the
                  attribute panel.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <noteGrp>
            <note target="#fn-m9ic2gkq-e2pwse">In more technical terms, the editor distinguishes
               between <hi rend="i">nodes</hi> and <hi rend="i">marks</hi>: while nodes are mostly
               block-level elements (with some exceptions), marks are lightweight markers attached
               to a piece of text.</note>
         </noteGrp>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>